<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short accovnt of the vniust proceedings of the Court of Kingstone upon Thames in a tryal between Richard Mayo, priest and E. Burrough, the 31 of the fifth moneth, 1658.</title>
            <author>Cooke, Edward, fl. 1658-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20657</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6006</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09673919</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09673919</idno>
            <idno type="VID">204443</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20657)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204443)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1328:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short accovnt of the vniust proceedings of the Court of Kingstone upon Thames in a tryal between Richard Mayo, priest and E. Burrough, the 31 of the fifth moneth, 1658.</title>
                  <author>Cooke, Edward, fl. 1658-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: Edw. Cooke.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mayo, Richard, 1631?-1695.</term>
               <term>Burrough, Edward, 1634-1662.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:204443:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204443:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Short ACCOVNT OF THE Vniuſt proceedings OF THE Court of <hi>Kingſtone</hi> upon <hi>Thames,</hi> IN A TRYAL between Richard Mayo, Prieſt, and E. Burrough, the 31. of the fifth Moneth, 1658.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>RIchard Mayo</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Kingſton,</hi> ſent for <hi>Edward Burough</hi> out of a Meeting in the Town, to come to the Steeple-houſe; and <hi>R. Mayo,</hi> divers times challenged <hi>E. B.</hi> that what he had againſt him and his Doctrine, there he might ſpeak it, and <hi>E. B.</hi> went to the Steeple-houſe, and heard <hi>R. Mayo</hi>'s Doctrine, who did Preach and affirm,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That</hi> Paul <hi>as a Miniſter of Chriſt, exhorted Saints (the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians) to follow and obey a light, which was not Chriſt, nor the light of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He did exhort the People of</hi> Kingſton, <hi>as a Miniſter of Chriſt, in his Preaching to them, to follow and obey a light which</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>is not Chriſt, nor the light of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He ſaid that a man may be a righteous man, and not a godly man, without diſtinction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Alſo at another time before that,</hi> R. Mayo <hi>affirmed, that the light of Chriſt, which every man is lightened withal,</hi> Joh. 1.9. <hi>is Carnal, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>He did affirm under his own hand, that Chriſt was not the word, that David walked by.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe Doctrines he could not prove by the Scriptures, being put upon it, and then <hi>E. B.</hi> ſaid that they were damnable Doctrines, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204443:2"/> errors, and not ſound, nor according to the truth; for which ſaying, an Action was entered, and <hi>E. B.</hi> was arreſted and impriſoned, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a yeer after was brought to tryal in the Court at <hi>Kingſton,</hi> and being called to his Anſwer in the Court, he lawfully proved by evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Witneſſes, all the particulars aforementioned, and the Prieſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to the things that he did affirm and preach them; And <hi>E. B.</hi> ſtill confeſſed and ſaid that theſe Doctrines were not ſound, but damnable and error, which were the words charged againſt him to be a ſlander: A Jury being called to hear and determine the matter <hi>E. B.</hi> deſired to be heard, and would have proved according to the Scriptures to the Jury and whole Court, that the Doctrines aforeſaid were damnable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, and errors: But the Judge, Jury and Court would not ſuffer him to be heard to manifeſt the truth: But the Judge told the Jury be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they went out, they might find good damage for the Prieſt; and the Jury went forth, and brought in <hi>E. B.</hi> guilty, and gave the Prieſt 100. <hi>l.</hi> damage for ſlandering him, and yet would not ſuffer E. B. to clear himſelf before they condemned him, but dealt unjuſtly againſt him. Now the light of Chriſt that lighteth every man that comes into the world, which is the life of men which was in the beginning with God, which <hi>Iohn</hi> came to <hi>bear witneſs of, that all might believe in him, and have eternal life: For all that received him that lighteneth every one that came into the world with the true light, he gave them power to become the ſons of God, Iohn</hi> 1. <hi>chap. Now this light which every man is lightened withall by Chriſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>R. Mayo) is carnal and darkneſſe;</hi> and that which is carnal and darkneſſe is of the fleſh and of the Devil. And the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Jury hath juſtified the Prieſt in ſo ſaying, and falſly damnified <hi>E. B.</hi> for ſaying this Doctrine is unſound and damnable: And this Prieſt, Jury and Court have gone about to prove that <hi>Iohn</hi> came to bear witneſſe of that which is carnal and darkneſs, who ſaith, he <hi>came for a witneſſe to bear witneſſe unto the true light, and that is the true light</hi> [ſaith <hi>Iohn] that lighteth every one that comes into the world:</hi> And this was <hi>Iohns</hi> Record; and this is the light which the Prieſt of <hi>Kingſton</hi> ſaith is carnal and darkneſſe, and the Jury and court hath juſtified him in it, and damnified <hi>E. B.</hi> for witneſſing to the contrary, and ſaying this is damnable Doctrine. Now that that is carnal and darkneſs, is earthly, fleſhly and devilliſh; but Chriſt nor his light is not earthly, fleſhly and devilliſh, but is from Heaven, and of the Spirit: And all that which is carnal and darkneſſe, is of the Devil and Devilliſh, and ſo is the light of Chriſt that lighteneth every man, by <hi>Rich. Mayo</hi>'s Doctrine; and the Judge and Jury hath juſtified that it is ſo, carnal and darkneſs, of the fleſh and of the Devil; but in Chriſt there is no darkneſs, for the Father and the Son are one, and God is light, and in him is no dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at all, the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> but this Prieſts Doctrine is quite contrary to <hi>Iohns</hi> Doctrine, and contrary to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204443:2"/> who hath held forth that the light of Chriſt is of the fleſh, and of the Devil, and therefore his Doctrine is damnable and error in the higheſt degree, and Chriſt ſaid, <hi>the Devil had nothing in him,</hi> Joh. 14.30. but <hi>Rich. Mayo</hi> ſaith, the light that Chriſt lighteth every one withall, which comes from Chriſt, is carnal and darkneſs (to wit) of the fleſh and of the devil, and ſo would make appear that the Devil and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had ſomething in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Darkneſs had no fellowshhip with light, nor Chriſt with Belial,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14. but <hi>R. Mayo</hi> holds forth that darkneſs is in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and would make Light and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs one; for he ſaith, the light of <hi>Chriſt</hi> which lightens every one, is darkneſs and carnal; but in this the Prieſt and Rulers of <hi>Kingſton</hi> hath ſhewed to all the world what <hi>Spirit</hi> they are of, and what they believe concerning <hi>Chriſt,</hi> even that his light which is pure and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, <hi>is of the flesh and of the devil, carnal and darkneſs,</hi> and its manifeſt they are uncapable of judging Doctrines; for to ſay and juſtifie as the Prieſt and Court of <hi>Kingſton</hi> hath done, that the <hi>light of Chriſt which lightneth every man,</hi> which <hi>Iohn</hi> came for a witneſs of, that all men through him ſhould believe, is <hi>carnal and darkneſs:</hi> It is blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, it is falſe, it is a lie, it is of the Devil, and damnable Doctrine, and he that affirms ſo is not fit to be a Teacher: and you that juſtifie him in it, and condemns him that reproves it, are not fit to be Judges of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Cauſe, nor of the things of God and <hi>Chriſt</hi> that are ſpiritual. And if the Judge and Iury ſay they do not own and believe that the light of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is carnal and darkneſs, then they have judged againſt their conſciences, and againſt their oaths, in condemning a man for denying this doctrine, and ſaying it is damnable; for is not carnal and darkneſs of the fleſh and of the devil, and out of the truth, and from below? And is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> from above, and from heaven? And is not his light ſo? You have judged like heathens, and like men without any underſtanding, and you have ſhewed your ſelves to be like the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Iews: Their Prieſts and Courts and Counſels, judged <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be a deceiver, and the Prince of Devils: And you ſay and do ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie it in your judgement, that <hi>Chriſts</hi> light which every man is light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned withall, is of the fleſh and of the devil; and ſo is carnal and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and have damnified a man for ſaying the contrary: and you have ſhewed your ſelves to be againſt Chriſt as much as ever the Jews were, and to be of the very ſame ſpirit: for you ſay and juſtifie <hi>That Chriſts Light is carnal and darkneſs:</hi> And they ſaid he <hi>was the Prince of Devils and Darkneſs:</hi> And do you not herefully agree with the Jews? The Apoſtle ſaid the Devil was the power of darkneſſe, and the Saints were tranſlated from the power of darkneſſe <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. But how doth <hi>Rich. Maoy</hi>'s Doctrine agree with this? Is the Devil the power of the light of Chriſt that lightneth every man? Is not this damnable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? But hereby the Prieſt and court of <hi>Kingſton</hi> have ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204443:3"/> to be in darkneſſe and carnal, which is a damnable ſtate: and it is damnable to ſay and judge of Chriſt as they have done, that dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is in him, and that his light which lighteneth the World, is of the fleſh and of the Devil: But with the light which every man is lightned withall, which is pure and eternal of God, are they judged that ſo jugde: and with the light ſhall they be condemned: that <hi>is the word of the Lord God to you all:</hi> And God will make you aſhamed of your judgement who know not Chriſt, and therefore have you falſly judged him, and judged quite contrary to <hi>Johns</hi> words, who ſaid <hi>that was the true light that lightneth every man;</hi> but you have ſaid and judged it is carnal and darkneſs; and will you ſay that that which is carnal and darkneſs is a true light? And if you ſay ſo, that is damnable Dotrine, and ſo you are in a ſnare, and hath brought a ſnate upon your your ſouls and have left your Names and Judgements a ſtink to all the Saints up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth.</p>
            <p>And the Judge, and Jury, and Court of <hi>Kingſtone</hi> have alſo jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it to be ſound Doctrine, to ſay, <hi>Paul exhorted the Saints te follow, and obey a light which is not Chriſt, nor the light of the Goſpel,</hi> which the Prieſt affirmed: Now here you have ſlandered the Apoſtle, and bely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and given a falſe judgement againſt him, as well as againſt <hi>E.B.</hi> for the Apoſtle did not exhort the Saints to follow any Light but what is Chriſt, and the light of the Goſpel; for hee ſaith often, that he preached the Goſpel and Chriſt the power of God, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all his writings, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. for hee was ſent <hi>To turne people from darkneſs to the light of the Goſpel,</hi> and from Satans power, (uhich is darkneſſe) to God, (who is light) <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. and hee turned people to <hi>Chriſt within them,</hi> who is the power of God, and the <hi>Goſpel is the power of God, Rom.</hi> 1.16. And ſaith hee, if any preach another Goſpel then what he had preached, let him be accurſed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.7.8. And he preached Chriſt unto the Saints, and the Goſpel onely, and deſired not to know any thing among them but <hi>Christ, and him cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> and that their Faith might ſtand in the power of God, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; and evary where he preached the Goſpel, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.9. and I affirm he preached nothing elſe, but Chriſt, the power of God, the Goſpel, to be obeyed and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; for it is that which convertcd to God, and it is that he exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Saints to walk by: <hi>Walk in the Spirit, and live in the Spirit, ſaith he, and obey the Spirit;</hi> and ſo ſhall you not fulfil the works of the fleſh; <hi>And as many as were the Sons of God, walked by the Spirit, and were led by the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8. and the Spirit, and the Goſpel, and Chriſt are one, and not many, nor divided. But this Prieſt, and Court of <hi>Kingſton</hi> have judged contraiy, even that <hi>Paul</hi> did Preach to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and obeyed, and believed in ſomething that is not the Light of the Goſpel, nor the Power of God, nor Chriſt, and ſo have ſlandered
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204443:3"/> and belyed the ſervant of the Lord the Apoſtle <hi>Paul:</hi> And is not this damnable to bely the Apoſtle? And is not this of the Devil, and Devilliſh doctrine, that ſlanders the ſervant of the Lord that is dead? but his ſpirit and words are a witneſs againſt them; it is out of the truth, and contrary to truth to belye and ſlander the Apoſtle; and that is of the Devil, and Damnable and Error: for every lye is out of the truth, and ſo of the Devil, and that which is of the Devill is Damnable, and muſt be caſt into the Lake with the Devil: And ſuch is <hi>R. Mayo</hi>'s doctrine.</p>
            <p>And <hi>R. Mayo</hi> in his Sermon, held forth as good doctrine, <hi>That the people of Kingſtone might follow and obey, and walk by a light which</hi> (hee ſaid) <hi>was not the light of the Goſpel,</hi> and exhorted them to it, and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them upon it, and yet he ſaid, <hi>It would not lead to Chriſt, nor reveal him to them,</hi> yet preſſed them to follow that Light: And this doctrine hath the Judge and Jury and Court juſtified to be ſound, and not falſe Doctrine, and have damnified <hi>E. B.</hi> for a Slanderer, for denying his doctrine, and ſaying, it is damnable. Now there is but Light and Darkneſs, God and Belial, Chriſt and Antichriſt; and if it be not the light of the power of God which is the Goſpel, which they are to follow, then it is darkneſs, and of the Devil which he exhorted them to follow; and if it be not Chriſt, nor God, nor the Spirit, which he preſſed them to obey, then it is Antichriſt, and that which is of the fleſh which they are exhorted to follow; and this is damnable: and if it be not the true Goſpel, the power of God, nor the light of it, nor Chriſt (as he ſaith it is not) then it is another Goſpel that hee hath preached in the Pulpet in <hi>Kingſtone,</hi> and he is accurſed that doth ſo, and accurſed Doctrine is danmable Doctrine, and a man that is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed is in a damnable ſtate, and they that follow and obey any other thing beſides Chriſt and the light of the Goſpel, they cannot be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; for this is ſaving doctrine, to preach Chriſt and his Goſpel one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>For there is no other name given under heaven to be ſaved by but Chriſt, Acts</hi> 4 12. Who is the power of God, the Goſpel, who is the light of life, the truth, to be obeyed and followed; and that doctrine that is otherwiſe and contrary to this, is damnable; and <hi>Richard Mayo</hi> hath preached another Doctrine, and hath preached that people ſhould follow and obey ſomething that is not Chriſt, nor the <hi>light</hi> of his Goſpel; and ſo his doctrine is not ſaving; for he hath preached another Name and another Light then <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Goſpel and the Judge and Jury have juſtified him in it, and judged E. B. for a ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, becauſe he ſaid this was unſound Doctrine, and Error, becauſe it is not the Doctrine of Chriſt nor his Goſpel, but another Doctrine, of another light, and of another way: But come Friends, is this Prieſt a Miniſter of Chriſt? And is this Court and Jury righteous Judges? let all the Saints that fear God upon Earth judge: Is not he a Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204443:4"/> who hath preached another Goſpel then <hi>Paul</hi> preached? Is he not one of Satans Meſſengers? and the Court hath upheld him in it; for there is no ſound Doctrine held forth by any of Chriſts Miniſters, but the Doctrine of Chriſt and of the Goſpel: This we all affirm with <hi>E.B.</hi> And all that owns not this Doctrine, and comes not to it, are in a damnable ſtate; And all Doctrine that is not juſtly according to this, is damnable, and they that hold it forth are deceivers and Satans Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers: And <hi>E.B.</hi> denies the judgement of all ſuch that doth not follow Chriſt, and walk in the light of the Goſpel, but believes that ſome other thing is to be obeyed and followed; and God wil confound their judgement, and bring the innocent to rejoice over all ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Judges.</p>
            <p>And <hi>R. Mayo</hi> the Prieſt affirms (and the Jury juſtifies it) <hi>That the Word that David walked by was not Chriſt,</hi> and hath judged <hi>E. B.</hi> guilty of ſlander for ſaying this Doctrine is Error, and to be condemned: Now <hi>David</hi> was of the ſeed, the fleſh of <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> is the word, and <hi>David</hi> followed <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the covenant of God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.6. And <hi>David</hi> was in the covenant, and followed Gods covenant, and ſaid <hi>the Lord was his light, Pſal.</hi> 27.1, and walked in <hi>Christ</hi> the word, the everlaſting covenant: And <hi>David</hi> was a follower of <hi>Chriſt</hi> the word, for <hi>David</hi> called Chriſt Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.1. And Chriſt was his Lord and his Shepherd, and fed him, and he led him into green paſtures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23. And <hi>David</hi> walked in the light of Chriſt, and ſaid, <hi>In thy Light we ſee Light, Pſal.</hi> 36.9. And he did walk by Chriſt the Word; And the Apoſtle often brings <hi>Davids</hi> words that were ſpoken of Chriſt; and Chriſts Name is the Word of God. And <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and all the Fathers ſaw the day of Chriſt, and eat and drank of the Rock that followed them; which Rock was <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and him they believed in, and obeyed. And <hi>David</hi> ſaw his reſurrection &amp; what ſhould betray him: And doth not <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſay, <hi>It is written in your Law, I ſaid you are Gods;</hi> if <hi>David</hi> were but onely in the Law? but he ſaw Chriſt the end of their offerings, and he was of the fleſh of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the ſeed; but theſe things are out of your underſtandings; ye are rather of that generation that mocked <hi>David:</hi> And to ſay <hi>David</hi> did not follow Chriſt, and was not a follower of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is error and damnable Doctrine. But the Prieſt and court of <hi>Kingſton</hi> have ſaid and judged that <hi>David</hi> did not walk by the word <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is falſe and a lye, and that's damnable, and of the Devil, and they have judged they know not what, they have put light for darkneſs, and darkneſs for light, and called good evil, and evil good; and have ſaid and judged con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Scriptures: Shall not God plead with them, and ſeven Vials of plagues ſhall be poured on the unjuſt, and all the Saints ſhall ſee their ſhame.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:204443:4"/>
            <p>And theſe with many other things which <hi>R. Mayo</hi> hath affirmed for Doctrine, doth <hi>E.B.</hi> charge to be falſe Doctrine, and not according to the Scriptures, and can prove theut to be falſe by the Scripture: But as if you were affraid to hear the truth, and durſt not ſtand to the trial, you would not ſuffer <hi>E.B.</hi> to prove theſe things in open Court, which he would have done according to the Scriptures. So this is written that all may ſee, and he may prove it over and over again, and publiſh it to all people to your ſhame; for God will make you aſhamed, and teare you to pieces, ye that have forgetten God, and neglected juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ye gnaw not the bones till the morrow; ye think ye have gotten a great deal of prey to devour, a hundred pounds, them that did ſo were like evening wolves, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.3. for this is the part of an evening wolfe, to leave the bones till the morrow. Think ye the Lord is blind like your ſelves, and that he ſees you not? And think ye <hi>E.B.</hi> hath ſpoken that which he is not able to make good? yes greater things then thoſe he may juſtly charge upon you, and among you, if you go on in injustice, may not he ſay ye pervert Juſtice and true Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Is it a ſlander to ſpeake the truth, to ſay the Devil is a lyar? though you would not hear him in the court, he may make the Nation hear him after this. Was <hi>Paul</hi> a ſlanderer that called one a childe of the Devil, that perverted the way of God, who was ſo? Was <hi>Iſaiah</hi> a ſlanderer that called the Shepherds greedy dumb dogs, end ſaid the people were like ſed Horſes, that neighed after their neighbors wives? the Prophet told the people they were fat Kine of <hi>Basban,</hi> and people were like wilde bulls in a net: But was the Prophets ſlanderers who told the ſalſe Prophets that they ſpoke a divination of their own brain, as <hi>R. Mayo</hi> hath done, and not from the mouth of the Lord? And the Prophets teſtified that the Judges judged for gifts and rewards, and were like Foxes in the deſarts, and were like evening wolves: but the Prophets were no ſlanderers, for they ſpake the truth: Nor Chriſt was no ſlanderer, who called them that ſtood praying in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, and were called of men Maſter, Serpents and Vipers, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23. and compared men to dogs and ſwine, and cryed wo againſt them, they were blind leaders of the blind. And what if you your ſelves be proved to be ſuch that brings forth fruit not meet for repentance, but are full of envy, bitterneſs and poyſon. Will it be a ſlander when a man calls you Vipers, and proves it that you are in that nature the Apoſtle called them <hi>Evil Beaſts, and ſlow bellies, that minded earthly things, and taught for filthy luere and love of money?</hi> And he was no ſlanderer who alſo ſaid they were accurſed that brought another Goſpel. And was the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Peter</hi> a ſlanderer who ſaid <hi>there were ſome that brought in damnable he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, for they denied the Lord that bought them:</hi> And this was a leſs tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion as men may account, to deny Chriſt, then to ſay his light is <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and darkneſs, of the fleſh &amp; of the devil,</hi> as the Prieſt &amp; unrighteous Jury
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204443:5"/> 
               <hi>Kingſton</hi> have done; for they did but deny him, but you ſlander him, and juſtifies that his light is carnal, and darkneſs of the fleſh, and of the devil, this is worſe then if you denied him, and ſaid nothing at all of him, and it is more damnable to ſlander him, that his light is carnal and darkneſs. Conſider of this, and be not ſo raſh; for ſhame in this life will come upon you, and judgement in the life to come, what ever become of <hi>E. B.</hi> in this life: You have ſhewed much folly and wickedneſs, both Prieſt, Iudges and Iury, who hath damnified a man an hundred pounds for ſpeaking the truth, and you have given a bad example to many others, but they that follow you in your works ſhall partake in the same judgement when the Lord gives you a juſt reward.</p>
            <p>And theſe are but few of the particulars which is proved damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Doctrine and Error. And <hi>E. B.</hi> hath many more particular ſayings and affirmations of <hi>R. Mayo</hi>'s, which to all the world may be proved the ſame with theſe; and if you go on, and will not revoke your works, he may lay them open, and all men may know what ſpirit <hi>R. Mayo</hi> is of: What will you think when he proves by many Witneſſes that <hi>R Mayo</hi> affirmed, <hi>That the Devil is the power of God;</hi> yea, <hi>even as the Goſpel is the power of God, ſaid he; and ſaid Chriſt was manifeſt to deſtroy the power of God, and him that is the power of God ſaid he; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the Goſpel to be the power of God?</hi> Theſe things with many more may be teſtified by many witneſſes before any Court in <hi>England:</hi> If you were quiet and did Juſtice, his ſhame and yours might be covered; but the more you ſtir and meddle among this filth, the more it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to ſhame you. And what need <hi>E.B.</hi> be affraid, or any man, what you can do? for truth is of his ſide, in compariſon of which his life is not dear, not liberty; and truth will ſhame you and pierce you to the hearts, and break you to pieces, though you may boaſt a while over it in your evil wayes, yet your day will the night of darkneſs ſhut up in miſery, and the bleſſing ſhall depart from you in this life, and in the life tO come: The Lord hath ſaid it, and ye that are froward the Lord will deal frowardly with you. Wherefore come to conſideration of this matter, and repent ye unrighteous men, and forſake this evil, and come to the light of God in your conſciences, that will let you ſee your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and prejudice againſt the innocent, and if you go in your evil courſe I am clear, it ſhall lye upon your own ſelves unto damnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hereafter a more full and large account of this matter you may expect from ſuch as hath a more perfect knowledge thereof, if the Court continue their injuſtice againſt the innocent.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By one that was a Witneſs of that day's proceedings, and a Witneſs againſt the injuſtice of it unto death, <hi>Edw. Cooke.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> 1658.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204443:5"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
